<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
        <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
        <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
        <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
        <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
        ]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="exp" docName="draft-przygienda-rift-dragonfly-00" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes=""
     submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
    <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.9.1 -->
    <front>
        <title abbrev="draft-przygienda-rift-dragonfly">
            RIFT in Dragonfly++ Topologies
        </title>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-przygienda-rift-dragonfly-00"/>
        <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="A." surname="Przygienda" role="editor">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1137 Innovation Way
                    </street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <region>CA
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>USA
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <email>prz@juniper.net
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date year="2023"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                RIFT support for dragonfly topologies as ToF interconnect.
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note>
            <name>Requirements Language</name>
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
                14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
                capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>

        <section toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>Introduction</name>
            <t>
                  RIFT today is standardized to deal with CLOS variant fabrics with some horizontal link exceptions.
                Given that
                interconnecting multiple CLOS via a dragonfly variant is an interesting topology (whether it's a full
                mesh or some kind of non-completely meshed regular lattice) this document addresses the resulting
                changes necessary to base RIFT specification to support dragonfly interconnected CLOS fabrics.
                The reader be advised that due to complexity of figures involved the ASCII version of the document
                leaves those out.
                To start, <xref target="oneplanesparsedf" /> visualizes three simple single plane
                fabrics interconnected via a DragonFly+ backbone. The behavior of standard RIFT is better understood
                if we look at the homomorphic version of the same topology in <xref target="oneplanesparsedf_homo" />.
                We can see that it is nothing else but a multi-plane CLOS with a lot of broken links for standard
                RIFT. The planes consist of S_x_1 and S_x_2 ToFs in each CLOS. Given this,
                leaf LB1 should be connected to SA1 to be in the plane and since it is not, SA1 will deduct that
                leaf LB1 fell off the plane 1 and negatively disaggregate it. Unfortunately the same is true for
                leaf LB1 from the view the SA2 in 2nd plane and it will negatively disaggregate it. Hence, leaf
                LA1 will not have any possibility to forward to LB1 using standard RIFT. This points us already
                to the first modification needed, we have to relax RIFT to forward through the horizontal
                links on ToFs and this will be the starting point of the next section.



            </t>

            <figure anchor="oneplanesparsedf">
                <name>Topologically Connected Planes</name>
                <artset>
                    <artwork align="center" name="" type="svg" src="prep/svg/oneplanesparsedf.svg"></artwork>
                    <artwork align="center" name="" type="ascii-art" src="svg/oneplanesparsedf.ascii-art"></artwork>
                </artset>
            </figure>

            <figure anchor="oneplanesparsedf_homo">
                <name>Topologically Connected Planes</name>
                <artset>
                    <artwork align="center" name="" type="svg" src="prep/svg/oneplanesparsedf_homomorphic.svg"></artwork>
                    <artwork align="center" name="" type="ascii-art" src="svg/oneplanesparsedf_homomorphic.ascii-art"></artwork>
                </artset>
            </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="glossary" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Glossary</name>
            <t>
                The following terms are used in this document.
            </t>
            <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
                <dt>Horizon:</dt>
                <dd>
                </dd>

            </dl>
        </section>


            <section numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Horizontal Link Behavior at ToF Level</name>
                <t>
                Dragonfly+, being basically a multi-plane CLOS with many broken links,
                    which we will call inter-fabric planes or IF planes to distinguish
                    them from multi-plane within a fabric
                    will need to change the behavior of RIFT to basically interconnect
                    multiple distinct CLOS fabrics via horizontal links at ToF level
                    that allow forwarding. Moreover, to deal with new mis-cabling
                    concepts we will not consider this configuration a single
                    fabric but a multi-fabric setup with "inter-fabric planes"
                    and allow ToF horizontal links only
                    to another fabric and moreover introduce
                    forwarding through such links to
                    distinguish those from normal "multi-plane ringing". Hence
                    in <xref target="oneplanesparsedf_homo" /> instead of
                    the first assumption of a single fabric we break out
                    fabric A and fabric B and consider the links SA2-SB2 and
                    SA1-SB1 two "inter-fabric DF+" links, in short IF-links.
                    Those links, just like all other horizontal ToF links
                    are considered southbound from both sides and northbound
                    flooding rules apply, an ideal thing since with that
                    all ToFs will see full topology of their inter-fabric
                    plane.

                </t>

                <t>
                    RIFT used in DF+ configuration will require on ToF not
                    only a ToF flag but a fabric ID now which has to be
                    distinct in each of the CLOS. In case of
                    non-DF+ mode the ToF will declare such links
                    miscabled, once enabled to be operate in DF+
                    it will mark those links as IF-links.
                    Given `fabric_id` is an optional schema element
                    a ToF operating in DF+ mode will reject all
                    links which have a ToF on the other side but
                    no `fabric_id` value set or do not indicate
                    DF+ mode as mis-cabled to prevent a mixture of
                    non-DF+ and DF+ ToFs in a setup.
                </t>

            </section>

        <section anchor="sec_route_comp" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>First, Simplest Route Computation Change</name>
            <t>
                Now that we can detect
                way IF-links reliably we can also remove those from the
                computations used in negative disaggregation as
                first step. This will prevent ToFs in fabric A
                negatively disaggregating Fabric B prefixes, a desirable
                behavior.
                Not being able to forward from Fabric A to
                fabric B is obviously a far less desirable behavior
                and hence a ToF in DF+ mode needs to extend its route
                computation by a special southbound DF+ computation
                where we use SPF taking in first step all IF links
                and the nodes behind them as candidates. This computation
                will result in a "direct inter-fabric forwarding database"
                with basically shortest path to prefixes in fabric B.
            </t>

            <section>
            <name>Additional Bi-Sectional Bandwidth Route Computation Change</name>

            <t>
                One of the DF+ properties is that it not only provides a direct
                path to a destination but guarantees that destinations are reachable
                via additional, alternate next-hop to increase the bi-sectional
                bandwidth. In our example SB1 forwarding to LA1 can take instead
                of SA1 directly a path through SC1 relying on it forwarding to SA1.
                To support this we introduce an additional SPF computation which
                takes in first 2 hops only the IF links is needed and generates
                a "indirect inter-fabric forwarding database". We will see later
                how those FIBs are used.
            </t>
            </section>

            <section>
                <name>Dragonfly with Multi-Plane CLOS Fabrics</name>
                <t>

                </t>
            </section>



        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Forwarding Considerations</name>
            <t>
                Since RIFT is being extended with the concept of "indirect
                inter-fabric next-hop" and IP packets carry not marking
                as the path they have taken indiscriminate forwarding
                using non-shortest paths at ToF level may loop
                in inter fabric case. To prevent this the ToFs have
                to maintain the concept of a "split horizon" on the
                arriving traffic. Any traffic arriving at the ToF
                that is targeted at the prefix within its fabric
                can be forwarded without any further considerations.
                On the other hand, traffic arriving at a inter-fabric
                link MUST use a FIB which does not contain the
                indirect inter-fabric next-hops. This will naturally
                limit any non-shortest inter-fabric path in ToF case to
                maximally one alternate next hop.

            </t>
        </section>


        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Schema Modifications</name>
        <t>
            To be provided in future version of the draft in detail. Basically
            the LIEs and Node TIEs need to be extended by fabric_id and DF+ mode
            indication.
        </t>
        </section>




        <section anchor="specialcons" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Special Considerations</name>

        <section anchor="patholody" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Partitioning of Inter-Fabric Planes</name>
            <t>
                A special case where a plane within a fabric breaks down
                is not noticeable in another fabric and hence the traffic
                can black hole. To detect the condition reliably
                a ToF has to compute the inter-fabric view of
                all the other ToFs in its own fabric and
                take the resulting difference as
                "inter-fabric negative disaggregation".
            </t>

        </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA" toc="default" numbered="true">
            <name>IANA Considerations</name>
            <t>This document requests allocation for the following RIFT codepoints.</t>
            <t>TBD</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Security Considerations</name>
            <t>
                TBD
            </t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Acknowledgements</name>
            <t>
                Dmitry Afanasiev based on his work with BGP and DF+ provided the crucial
                split horizon forwarding idea.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references>
            <name>References</name>
            <references>
                <name>Informative References</name>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8099.xml"/>

            </references>
            <references>
                <name>Normative References</name>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5302.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5304.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7775.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7981.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9012.xml"/>
            </references>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
